<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-17.09">

<title>Release 17.09 (“Hummingbird”, 2017/09/??)</title>

<para>In addition to numerous new and upgraded packages, this release
has the following highlights: </para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The user handling now keeps track of deallocated UIDs/GIDs. When a user
      or group is revived, this allows it to be allocated the UID/GID it had before.
      A consequence is that UIDs and GIDs are no longer reused.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The module option <option>services.xserver.xrandrHeads</option> now
      causes the first head specified in this list to be set as the primary
      head. Apart from that, it's now possible to also set additional options
      by using an attribute set, for example:
<programlisting>
{ services.xserver.xrandrHeads = [
    "HDMI-0"
    {
      output = &quot;DVI-0&quot;;
      primary = true;
      monitorConfig = ''
        Option &quot;Rotate&quot; &quot;right&quot;
      '';
    }
  ];
}
</programlisting>
      This will set the <literal>DVI-0</literal> output to be the primary head,
      even though <literal>HDMI-0</literal> is the first head in the list.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The following new services were added since the last release:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para></para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<para>When upgrading from a previous release, please be aware of the
following incompatible changes:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>aiccu</literal> package was removed. This is due to SixXS
      <link xlink:href="https://www.sixxs.net/main/"> sunsetting</link> its IPv6 tunnel.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Top-level <literal>idea</literal> package collection was renamed.
      All JetBrains IDEs are now at <literal>jetbrains</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>flexget</literal>'s state database cannot be upgraded to its
      new internal format, requiring removal of any existing
      <literal>db-config.sqlite</literal> which will be automatically recreated.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The ipfs package now doesn't ignore the <literal>dataDir</literal> option anymore. If you've ever set this option to anything other than the default you'll have to either unset it (so the default gets used) or migrate the old data manually with
<programlisting>
dataDir=&lt;valueOfDataDir&gt;
mv /var/lib/ipfs/.ipfs/* $dataDir
rmdir /var/lib/ipfs/.ipfs
</programlisting>
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The following changes apply if the <literal>stateVersion</literal> is changed to 17.09 or higher.
      For <literal>stateVersion = "17.03</literal> or lower the old behavior is preserved.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>postgres</literal> default version was changed from 9.5 to 9.6.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>postgres</literal> superuser name has changed from <literal>root</literal> to <literal>postgres</literal> to more closely follow what other Linux distributions are doing.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>postgres</literal> default <literal>dataDir</literal> has changed from <literal>/var/db/postgres</literal> to <literal>/var/lib/postgresql/$psqlSchema</literal> where $psqlSchema is 9.6 for example.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>mysql</literal> default <literal>dataDir</literal> has changed from <literal>/var/mysql</literal> to <literal>/var/lib/mysql</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The <literal>caddy</literal> service was previously using an extra
      <literal>.caddy</literal> in the data directory specified with the
      <literal>dataDir</literal> option. The contents of the
      <literal>.caddy</literal> directory are now expected to be in the
      <literal>dataDir</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The <literal>ssh-agent</literal> user service is not started by default
      anymore. Use <literal>programs.ssh.startAgent</literal> to enable it if
      needed. There is also a new <literal>programs.gnupg.agent</literal>
      module that creates a <literal>gpg-agent</literal> user service. It can
      also serve as a SSH agent if <literal>enableSSHSupport</literal> is set.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The <literal>services.tinc.networks.&lt;name&gt;.listenAddress</literal>
      option had a misleading name that did not correspond to its behavior. It
      now correctly defines the ip to listen for incoming connections on. To
      keep the previous behaviour, use
      <literal>services.tinc.networks.&lt;name&gt;.bindToAddress</literal>
      instead. Refer to the description of the options for more details.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>tlsdate</literal> package and module were removed. This is due to the project
      being dead and not building with openssl 1.1.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>wvdial</literal> package and module were removed. This is due to the project
      being dead and not building with openssl 1.1.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>cc-wrapper</literal>'s setup-hook now exports a number of
      environment variables corresponding to binutils binaries,
      (e.g. <envar>LD</envar>, <envar>STRIP</envar>, <envar>RANLIB</envar>,
      etc). This is done to prevent packages' build systems guessing, which is
      harder to predict, especially when cross-compiling. However, some packages
      have broken due to this—their build systems either not supporting, or
      claiming to support without adequate testing, taking such environment
      variables as parameters.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Other notable improvements:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>
      Modules can now be disabled by using <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/nixpkgs/manual/#sec-replace-modules">
      disabledModules</link>, allowing another to take it's place.  This can be
      used to import a set of modules from another channel while keeping the
      rest of the system on a stable release.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Updated to FreeType 2.7.1, including a new TrueType engine.
      The new engine replaces the Infinality engine which was the default in
      NixOS. The default font rendering settings are now provided by
      fontconfig-penultimate, replacing fontconfig-ultimate; the new defaults
      are less invasive and provide rendering that is more consistent with
      other systems and hopefully with each font designer's intent. Some
      system-wide configuration has been removed from the Fontconfig NixOS
      module where user Fontconfig settings are available.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      ZFS/SPL have been updated to 0.7.0, <literal>zfsUnstable, splUnstable</literal>
      have therefore been removed.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The <option>time.timeZone</option> option now allows the value
      <literal>null</literal> in addition to timezone strings. This value
      allows changing the timezone of a system imperatively using
      <command>timedatectl set-timezone</command>. The default timezone
      is still UTC.
    </para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</section>
