<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-17.09">

<title>Release 17.09 (“Hummingbird”, 2017/09/??)</title>

<para>In addition to numerous new and upgraded packages, this release
has the following highlights: </para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The user handling now keeps track of deallocated UIDs/GIDs. When a user
      or group is revived, this allows it to be allocated the UID/GID it had before.
      A consequence is that UIDs and GIDs are no longer reused.
    </para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>The following new services were added since the last release:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para></para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<para>When upgrading from a previous release, please be aware of the
following incompatible changes:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Top-level <literal>idea</literal> package collection was renamed.
      All JetBrains IDEs are now at <literal>jetbrains</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>flexget</literal>'s state database cannot be upgraded to its
      new internal format, requiring removal of any existing
      <literal>db-config.sqlite</literal> which will be automatically recreated.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<para>Other notable improvements:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>
      Modules can now be disabled by using <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/nixpkgs/manual/#sec-replace-modules">
      disabledModules</link>, allowing another to take it's place.  This can be
      used to import a set of modules from another channel while keeping the
      rest of the system on a stable release.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Updated to FreeType 2.7.1, including a new TrueType engine.
      The new engine replaces the Infinality engine which was the default in
      NixOS. The default font rendering settings are now provided by
      fontconfig-penultimate, replacing fontconfig-ultimate; the new defaults
      are less invasive and provide rendering that is more consistent with
      other systems and hopefully with each font designer's intent. Some
      system-wide configuration has been removed from the Fontconfig NixOS
      module where user Fontconfig settings are available.
    </para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</section>
