<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-21.03">
 <title>Release 21.03 (“Okapi”, 2021.03/??)</title>

 <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-21.03-highlights">
  <title>Highlights</title>

  <para>
   In addition to numerous new and upgraded packages, this release has the
   following highlights:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Support is planned until the end of October 2021, handing over to 21.09.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>GNOME desktop environment was upgraded to 3.38, see its <link xlink:href="https://help.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.38/">release notes</link>.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://www.gnuradio.org/">GNURadio</link> 3.8 was
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/issues/82263">finnally</link>
     packaged, along with a rewrite to the Nix expressions, allowing users to
     override the features upstream supports selecting to compile or not to.
     Additionally, the attribute <code>gnuradio</code> and <code>gnuradio3_7</code>
     now point to an externally wrapped by default derivations, that allow you to
     also add `extraPythonPackages` to the Python interpreter used by GNURadio.
     Missing environmental variables needed for operational GUI were also added
     (<link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/issues/75478">#7547</link>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-21.03-new-services">
  <title>New Services</title>

  <para>
   The following new services were added since the last release:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       <link xlink:href="https://www.keycloak.org/">Keycloak</link>,
       an open source identity and access management server with
       support for <link
       xlink:href="https://openid.net/connect/">OpenID Connect</link>,
       <link xlink:href="https://oauth.net/2/">OAUTH 2.0</link> and
       <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SAML_2.0">SAML
       2.0</link>.
     </para>
     <para>
       See the <link linkend="module-services-keycloak">Keycloak
       section of the NixOS manual</link> for more information.
     </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       <xref linkend="opt-services.samba-wsdd.enable" /> Web Services Dynamic Discovery host daemon
     </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

 </section>

 <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-21.03-incompatibilities">
  <title>Backward Incompatibilities</title>

  <para>
   When upgrading from a previous release, please be aware of the following
   incompatible changes:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <literal>systemd-journal2gelf</literal> no longer parses json and expects the receiving system to handle it. How to achieve this with Graylog is described in this <link xlink:href="https://github.com/parse-nl/SystemdJournal2Gelf/issues/10">GitHub issue</link>.
      </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the <varname>services.dbus</varname> module is enabled, then
     the user D-Bus session is now always socket activated. The
     associated options <varname>services.dbus.socketActivated</varname>
     and <varname>services.xserver.startDbusSession</varname> have
     therefore been removed and you will receive a warning if
     they are present in your configuration. This change makes the
     user D-Bus session available also for non-graphical logins.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       <literal>rubyMinimal</literal> was removed due to being unused and
       unusable. The default ruby interpreter includes JIT support, which makes
       it reference it's compiler. Since JIT support is probably needed by some
       Gems, it was decided to enable this feature with all cc references by
       default, and allow to build a Ruby derivation without references to cc,
       by setting <literal>jitSupport = false;</literal> in an overlay. See
       <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/pull/90151">#90151</link>
       for more info.
     </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       Setting <option>services.openssh.authorizedKeysFiles</option> now also affects which keys <option>security.pam.enableSSHAgentAuth</option> will use.

       WARNING: If you are using these options in combination do make sure that any key paths you use are present in <option>services.openssh.authorizedKeysFiles</option>!
     </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The option <option>fonts.enableFontDir</option> has been renamed to
     <xref linkend="opt-fonts.fontDir.enable"/>. The path of font directory
     has also been changed to <literal>/run/current-system/sw/share/X11/fonts</literal>,
     for consistency with other X11 resources.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      A number of options have been renamed in the kicad interface. <literal>oceSupport</literal>
      has been renamed to <literal>withOCE</literal>, <literal>withOCCT</literal> has been renamed
      to <literal>withOCC</literal>, <literal>ngspiceSupport</literal> has been renamed to
      <literal>withNgspice</literal>, and <literal>scriptingSupport</literal> has been renamed to
      <literal>withScripting</literal>. Additionally, <literal>kicad/base.nix</literal> no longer
      provides default argument values since these are provided by
      <literal>kicad/default.nix</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      The socket for the <literal>pdns-recursor</literal> module was moved from <literal>/var/lib/pdns-recursor</literal>
      to <literal>/run/pdns-recursor</literal> to match upstream.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Paperwork was updated to version 2. The on-disk format slightly changed,
      and it is not possible to downgrade from Paperwork 2 back to Paperwork
      1.3. Back your documents up before upgrading. See <link xlink:href="https://forum.openpaper.work/t/paperwork-2-0/112/5">this thread</link> for more details.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      PowerDNS has been updated from <literal>4.2.x</literal> to <literal>4.3.x</literal>. Please
      be sure to review the <link xlink:href="https://doc.powerdns.com/authoritative/upgrading.html#x-to-4-3-0">Upgrade Notes</link>
      provided by upstream before upgrading. Worth specifically noting is that the service now runs
      entirely as a dedicated <literal>pdns</literal> user, instead of starting as <literal>root</literal>
      and dropping privileges, as well as the default <literal>socket-dir</literal> location changing from
      <literal>/var/lib/powerdns</literal> to <literal>/run/pdns</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    <package>btc1</package> has been abandoned upstream, and removed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    <package>cpp_ethereum</package> (aleth) has been abandoned upstream, and removed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    <package>riak-cs</package> package removed along with <varname>services.riak-cs</varname> module.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    <package>stanchion</package> package removed along with <varname>services.stanchion</varname> module.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>mutt</package> has been updated to a new major version (2.x), which comes with
     some backward incompatible changes that are described in the
     <link xlink:href="http://www.mutt.org/relnotes/2.0/">release notes for Mutt 2.0</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      <literal>vim</literal> switched to Python 3, dropping all Python 2 support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
      <link linkend="opt-boot.zfs.forceImportAll">boot.zfs.forceImportAll</link>
      previously did nothing, but has been fixed. However its default has been
      changed to <literal>false</literal> to preserve the existing default
      behaviour. If you have this explicitly set to <literal>true</literal>,
      please note that your non-root pools will now be forcibly imported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>openafs</package> now points to <package>openafs_1_8</package>,
     which is the new stable release.  OpenAFS 1.6 was removed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      The <literal>openldap</literal> module now has support for OLC-style
      configuration, users of the <literal>configDir</literal> option may wish
      to migrate. If you continue to use <literal>configDir</literal>, ensure that
      <literal>olcPidFile</literal> is set to <literal>/run/slapd/slapd.pid</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
      As a result, <literal>extraConfig</literal> and <literal>extraDatabaseConfig</literal>
      are removed. To help with migration, you can convert your <literal>slapd.conf</literal>
      file to OLC configuration with the following script (find the location of this
      configuration file by running <literal>systemctl status openldap</literal>, it is the
      <literal>-f</literal> option.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      TMPDIR=$(mktemp -d)
      slaptest -f /path/to/slapd.conf $TMPDIR
      slapcat -F $TMPDIR -n0 -H 'ldap:///???(!(objectClass=olcSchemaConfig))'
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      This will dump your current configuration in LDIF format, which should be
      straightforward to convert into Nix settings. This does not show your schema
      configuration, as this is unnecessarily verbose for users of the default schemas
      and <literal>slaptest</literal> is buggy with schemas directly in the config file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       Amazon EC2 and OpenStack Compute (nova) images now re-fetch instance meta data and user data from the instance
       metadata service (IMDS) on each boot. For example: stopping an EC2 instance, changing its user data, and
       restarting the instance will now cause it to fetch and apply the new user data.
     </para>
     <warning>
       <para>
         Specifically, <literal>/etc/ec2-metadata</literal> is re-populated on each boot. Some NixOS scripts that read
         from this directory are guarded to only run if the files they want to manipulate do not already exist, and so
         will not re-apply their changes if the IMDS response changes. Examples: <literal>root</literal>'s SSH key is
         only added if <literal>/root/.ssh/authorized_keys</literal> does not exist, and SSH host keys are only set from
         user data if they do not exist in <literal>/etc/ssh</literal>.
       </para>
     </warning>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      The <literal>rspamd</literal> services is now sandboxed. It is run as
      a dynamic user instead of root, so secrets and other files may have to
      be moved or their permissions may have to be fixed. The sockets are now
      located in <literal>/run/rspamd</literal> instead of <literal>/run</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Enabling the Tor client no longer silently also enables and
      configures Privoxy, and the
      <varname>services.tor.client.privoxy.enable</varname> option has
      been removed.  To enable Privoxy, and to configure it to use
      Tor's faster port, use the following configuration:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      <xref linkend="opt-services.privoxy.enable" /> = true;
      <xref linkend="opt-services.privoxy.enableTor" /> = true;
    </programlisting>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       The options <literal>services.slurm.dbdserver.storagePass</literal>
       and <literal>services.slurm.dbdserver.configFile</literal> have been removed.
       Use <literal>services.slurm.dbdserver.storagePassFile</literal> instead to provide the database password.
       Extra config options can be given via the option <literal>services.slurm.dbdserver.extraConfig</literal>. The actual configuration file is created on the fly on startup of the service.
       This avoids that the password gets exposed in the nix store.
     </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       Starting with version 1.7.0, the project formerly named <literal>CodiMD</literal>
       is now named <literal>HedgeDoc</literal>.
       New installations will no longer use the old name for users, state directories and such, this needs to be considered when moving state to a more recent NixOS installation.
       Based on <xref linkend="opt-system.stateVersion" />, existing installations will continue to work.
     </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="sec-release-21.03-notable-changes">
  <title>Other Notable Changes</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Mailman NixOS module (<literal>services.mailman</literal>) has a new
     option <xref linkend="opt-services.mailman.enablePostfix" />, defaulting
     to true, that controls integration with Postfix.
    </para>
    <para>
     If this option is disabled, default MTA config becomes not set and you
     should set the options in <literal>services.mailman.settings.mta</literal>
     according to the desired configuration as described in
     <link xlink:href="https://mailman.readthedocs.io/en/latest/src/mailman/docs/mta.html">Mailman documentation</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The default-version of <literal>nextcloud</literal> is <package>nextcloud20</package>.
     Please note that it's <emphasis>not</emphasis> possible to upgrade <literal>nextcloud</literal>
     across multiple major versions! This means that it's e.g. not possible to upgrade
     from <package>nextcloud18</package> to <package>nextcloud20</package> in a single deploy.
    </para>
    <para>
     The package can be manually upgraded by setting <xref linkend="opt-services.nextcloud.package" />
     to <package>nextcloud20</package>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The setting <xref linkend="opt-services.redis.bind" /> defaults to <literal>127.0.0.1</literal> now, making Redis listen on the loopback interface only, and not all public network interfaces.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     NixOS now emits a deprecation warning if systemd's <literal>StartLimitInterval</literal> setting is used in a <literal>serviceConfig</literal> section instead of in a <literal>unitConfig</literal>; that setting is deprecated and now undocumented for the service section by systemd upstream, but still effective and somewhat buggy there, which can be confusing. See <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/issues/45785">#45785</link> for details.
    </para>
    <para>
     All services should use <xref linkend="opt-systemd.services._name_.startLimitIntervalSec" /> or <literal>StartLimitIntervalSec</literal> in <xref linkend="opt-systemd.services._name_.unitConfig" /> instead.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Unbound DNS resolver service (<literal>services.unbound</literal>) has been refactored to allow reloading, control sockets and to fix startup ordering issues.
    </para>

    <para>
     It is now possible to enable a local UNIX control socket for unbound by setting the <xref linkend="opt-services.unbound.localControlSocketPath" />
     option.
    </para>

    <para>
     Previously we just applied a very minimal set of restrictions and
     trusted unbound to properly drop root privs and capabilities.
    </para>

    <para>
     As of this we are (for the most part) just using the upstream
     example unit file for unbound. The main difference is that we start
     unbound as <literal>unbound</literal> user with the required capabilities instead of
     letting unbound do the chroot &amp; uid/gid changes.
    </para>

    <para>
     The upstream unit configuration this is based on is a lot stricter with
     all kinds of permissions then our previous variant. It also came with
     the default of having the <literal>Type</literal> set to <literal>notify</literal>, therefore we are now also
     using the <literal>unbound-with-systemd</literal> package here. Unbound will start up,
     read the configuration files and start listening on the configured ports
     before systemd will declare the unit <literal>active (running)</literal>.
     This will likely help with startup order and the occasional race condition during system
     activation where the DNS service is started but not yet ready to answer
     queries. Services depending on <literal>nss-lookup.target</literal> or <literal>unbound.service</literal>
     are now be able to use unbound when those targets have been reached.
    </para>

    <para>
     Aditionally to the much stricter runtime environmet the
     <literal>/dev/urandom</literal> mount lines we previously had in the code (that would
     randomly failed during the stop-phase) have been removed as systemd will take care of those for us.
    </para>

    <para>
     The <literal>preStart</literal> script is now only required if we enabled the trust
      anchor updates (which are still enabled by default).
    </para>

    <para>
     Another benefit of the refactoring is that we can now issue reloads via
     either <literal>pkill -HUP unbound</literal> and <literal>systemctl reload unbound</literal> to reload the
     running configuration without taking the daemon offline. A prerequisite
     of this was that unbound configuration is available on a well known path
     on the file system. We are using the path <literal>/etc/unbound/unbound.conf</literal> as that is the
     default in the CLI tooling which in turn enables us to use
     <literal>unbound-control</literal> without passing a custom configuration location.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <literal>services.dnscrypt-proxy2</literal> module now takes the upstream's example configuration and updates it with the user's settings.

     An option has been added to restore the old behaviour if you prefer to declare the configuration from scratch.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     NixOS now defaults to the unified cgroup hierarchy (cgroupsv2).
     See the <link xlink:href="https://www.redhat.com/sysadmin/fedora-31-control-group-v2">Fedora Article for 31</link>
     for details on why this is desirable, and how it impacts containers.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you want to run containers with a runtime that does not yet support cgroupsv2,
     you can switch back to the old behaviour by setting
     <xref linkend="opt-systemd.enableUnifiedCgroupHierarchy"/> = <literal>false</literal>;
     and rebooting.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     PulseAudio was upgraded to 14.0, with changes to the handling of default sinks.
     See its <link xlink:href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/PulseAudio/Notes/14.0/">release notes</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
     GNOME users may wish to delete their <literal>~/.config/pulse</literal> due to the changes to stream routing
     logic. See <link xlink:href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/pulseaudio/pulseaudio/-/issues/832">PulseAudio bug 832</link>
     for more information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <package>zookeeper</package> package does not provide
     <literal>zooInspector.sh</literal> anymore, as that "contrib" has
     been dropped from upstream releases.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="opt-users.users._name_.createHome" /> now always ensures home directory permissions to be <literal>0700</literal>.
     Permissions had previously been ignored for already existing home directories, possibly leaving them readable by others.
     The option's description was incorrect regarding ownership management and has been simplified greatly.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
