<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="chap-functions">
 <title>Functions reference</title>
 <para>
  The nixpkgs repository has several utility functions to manipulate Nix
  expressions.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="sec-overrides">
  <title>Overriding</title>

  <para>
   Sometimes one wants to override parts of <literal>nixpkgs</literal>, e.g.
   derivation attributes, the results of derivations or even the whole package
   set.
  </para>

  <section xml:id="sec-pkg-override">
   <title>&lt;pkg&gt;.override</title>

   <para>
    The function <varname>override</varname> is usually available for all the
    derivations in the nixpkgs expression (<varname>pkgs</varname>).
   </para>

   <para>
    It is used to override the arguments passed to a function.
   </para>

   <para>
    Example usages:
<programlisting>pkgs.foo.override { arg1 = val1; arg2 = val2; ... }</programlisting>
<programlisting>import pkgs.path { overlays = [ (self: super: {
    foo = super.foo.override { barSupport = true ; };
  })]};</programlisting>
<programlisting>mypkg = pkgs.callPackage ./mypkg.nix {
    mydep = pkgs.mydep.override { ... };
  }</programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
    In the first example, <varname>pkgs.foo</varname> is the result of a
    function call with some default arguments, usually a derivation. Using
    <varname>pkgs.foo.override</varname> will call the same function with the
    given new arguments.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-pkg-overrideAttrs">
   <title>&lt;pkg&gt;.overrideAttrs</title>

   <para>
    The function <varname>overrideAttrs</varname> allows overriding the
    attribute set passed to a <varname>stdenv.mkDerivation</varname> call,
    producing a new derivation based on the original one. This function is
    available on all derivations produced by the
    <varname>stdenv.mkDerivation</varname> function, which is most packages in
    the nixpkgs expression <varname>pkgs</varname>.
   </para>

   <para>
    Example usage:
<programlisting>helloWithDebug = pkgs.hello.overrideAttrs (oldAttrs: rec {
    separateDebugInfo = true;
  });</programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
    In the above example, the <varname>separateDebugInfo</varname> attribute is
    overridden to be true, thus building debug info for
    <varname>helloWithDebug</varname>, while all other attributes will be
    retained from the original <varname>hello</varname> package.
   </para>

   <para>
    The argument <varname>oldAttrs</varname> is conventionally used to refer to
    the attr set originally passed to <varname>stdenv.mkDerivation</varname>.
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     Note that <varname>separateDebugInfo</varname> is processed only by the
     <varname>stdenv.mkDerivation</varname> function, not the generated, raw
     Nix derivation. Thus, using <varname>overrideDerivation</varname> will not
     work in this case, as it overrides only the attributes of the final
     derivation. It is for this reason that <varname>overrideAttrs</varname>
     should be preferred in (almost) all cases to
     <varname>overrideDerivation</varname>, i.e. to allow using
     <varname>sdenv.mkDerivation</varname> to process input arguments, as well
     as the fact that it is easier to use (you can use the same attribute names
     you see in your Nix code, instead of the ones generated (e.g.
     <varname>buildInputs</varname> vs <varname>nativeBuildInputs</varname>,
     and involves less typing.
    </para>
   </note>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-pkg-overrideDerivation">
   <title>&lt;pkg&gt;.overrideDerivation</title>

   <warning>
    <para>
     You should prefer <varname>overrideAttrs</varname> in almost all cases,
     see its documentation for the reasons why.
     <varname>overrideDerivation</varname> is not deprecated and will continue
     to work, but is less nice to use and does not have as many abilities as
     <varname>overrideAttrs</varname>.
    </para>
   </warning>

   <warning>
    <para>
     Do not use this function in Nixpkgs as it evaluates a Derivation before
     modifying it, which breaks package abstraction and removes error-checking
     of function arguments. In addition, this evaluation-per-function
     application incurs a performance penalty, which can become a problem if
     many overrides are used. It is only intended for ad-hoc customisation,
     such as in <filename>~/.config/nixpkgs/config.nix</filename>.
    </para>
   </warning>

   <para>
    The function <varname>overrideDerivation</varname> creates a new derivation
    based on an existing one by overriding the original's attributes with the
    attribute set produced by the specified function. This function is
    available on all derivations defined using the
    <varname>makeOverridable</varname> function. Most standard
    derivation-producing functions, such as
    <varname>stdenv.mkDerivation</varname>, are defined using this function,
    which means most packages in the nixpkgs expression,
    <varname>pkgs</varname>, have this function.
   </para>

   <para>
    Example usage:
<programlisting>mySed = pkgs.gnused.overrideDerivation (oldAttrs: {
    name = "sed-4.2.2-pre";
    src = fetchurl {
      url = ftp://alpha.gnu.org/gnu/sed/sed-4.2.2-pre.tar.bz2;
      sha256 = "11nq06d131y4wmf3drm0yk502d2xc6n5qy82cg88rb9nqd2lj41k";
    };
    patches = [];
  });</programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
    In the above example, the <varname>name</varname>, <varname>src</varname>,
    and <varname>patches</varname> of the derivation will be overridden, while
    all other attributes will be retained from the original derivation.
   </para>

   <para>
    The argument <varname>oldAttrs</varname> is used to refer to the attribute
    set of the original derivation.
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     A package's attributes are evaluated *before* being modified by the
     <varname>overrideDerivation</varname> function. For example, the
     <varname>name</varname> attribute reference in <varname>url =
     "mirror://gnu/hello/${name}.tar.gz";</varname> is filled-in *before* the
     <varname>overrideDerivation</varname> function modifies the attribute set.
     This means that overriding the <varname>name</varname> attribute, in this
     example, *will not* change the value of the <varname>url</varname>
     attribute. Instead, we need to override both the <varname>name</varname>
     *and* <varname>url</varname> attributes.
    </para>
   </note>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-lib-makeOverridable">
   <title>lib.makeOverridable</title>

   <para>
    The function <varname>lib.makeOverridable</varname> is used to make the
    result of a function easily customizable. This utility only makes sense for
    functions that accept an argument set and return an attribute set.
   </para>

   <para>
    Example usage:
<programlisting>f = { a, b }: { result = a+b; }
  c = lib.makeOverridable f { a = 1; b = 2; }</programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
    The variable <varname>c</varname> is the value of the <varname>f</varname>
    function applied with some default arguments. Hence the value of
    <varname>c.result</varname> is <literal>3</literal>, in this example.
   </para>

   <para>
    The variable <varname>c</varname> however also has some additional
    functions, like <link linkend="sec-pkg-override">c.override</link> which
    can be used to override the default arguments. In this example the value of
    <varname>(c.override { a = 4; }).result</varname> is 6.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-generators">
  <title>Generators</title>

  <para>
   Generators are functions that create file formats from nix data structures,
   e. g. for configuration files. There are generators available for:
   <literal>INI</literal>, <literal>JSON</literal> and <literal>YAML</literal>
  </para>

  <para>
   All generators follow a similar call interface: <code>generatorName
   configFunctions data</code>, where <literal>configFunctions</literal> is an
   attrset of user-defined functions that format nested parts of the content.
   They each have common defaults, so often they do not need to be set
   manually. An example is <code>mkSectionName ? (name: libStr.escape [ "[" "]"
   ] name)</code> from the <literal>INI</literal> generator. It receives the
   name of a section and sanitizes it. The default
   <literal>mkSectionName</literal> escapes <literal>[</literal> and
   <literal>]</literal> with a backslash.
  </para>

  <para>
   Generators can be fine-tuned to produce exactly the file format required by
   your application/service. One example is an INI-file format which uses
   <literal>: </literal> as separator, the strings
   <literal>"yes"</literal>/<literal>"no"</literal> as boolean values and
   requires all string values to be quoted:
  </para>

<programlisting>
with lib;
let
  customToINI = generators.toINI {
    # specifies how to format a key/value pair
    mkKeyValue = generators.mkKeyValueDefault {
      # specifies the generated string for a subset of nix values
      mkValueString = v:
             if v == true then ''"yes"''
        else if v == false then ''"no"''
        else if isString v then ''"${v}"''
        # and delegats all other values to the default generator
        else generators.mkValueStringDefault {} v;
    } ":";
  };

# the INI file can now be given as plain old nix values
in customToINI {
  main = {
    pushinfo = true;
    autopush = false;
    host = "localhost";
    port = 42;
  };
  mergetool = {
    merge = "diff3";
  };
}
</programlisting>

  <para>
   This will produce the following INI file as nix string:
  </para>

<programlisting>
[main]
autopush:"no"
host:"localhost"
port:42
pushinfo:"yes"
str\:ange:"very::strange"

[mergetool]
merge:"diff3"
</programlisting>

  <note>
   <para>
    Nix store paths can be converted to strings by enclosing a derivation
    attribute like so: <code>"${drv}"</code>.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   Detailed documentation for each generator can be found in
   <literal>lib/generators.nix</literal>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-debug">
  <title>Debugging Nix Expressions</title>

  <para>
   Nix is a unityped, dynamic language, this means every value can potentially
   appear anywhere. Since it is also non-strict, evaluation order and what
   ultimately is evaluated might surprise you. Therefore it is important to be
   able to debug nix expressions.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the <literal>lib/debug.nix</literal> file you will find a number of
   functions that help (pretty-)printing values while evaluation is runnnig.
   You can even specify how deep these values should be printed recursively,
   and transform them on the fly. Please consult the docstrings in
   <literal>lib/debug.nix</literal> for usage information.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-fhs-environments">
  <title>buildFHSUserEnv</title>

  <para>
   <function>buildFHSUserEnv</function> provides a way to build and run
   FHS-compatible lightweight sandboxes. It creates an isolated root with bound
   <filename>/nix/store</filename>, so its footprint in terms of disk space
   needed is quite small. This allows one to run software which is hard or
   unfeasible to patch for NixOS -- 3rd-party source trees with FHS
   assumptions, games distributed as tarballs, software with integrity checking
   and/or external self-updated binaries. It uses Linux namespaces feature to
   create temporary lightweight environments which are destroyed after all
   child processes exit, without root user rights requirement. Accepted
   arguments are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>name</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Environment name.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>targetPkgs</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages to be installed for the main host's architecture (i.e. x86_64 on
      x86_64 installations). Along with libraries binaries are also installed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>multiPkgs</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages to be installed for all architectures supported by a host (i.e.
      i686 and x86_64 on x86_64 installations). Only libraries are installed by
      default.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>extraBuildCommands</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Additional commands to be executed for finalizing the directory
      structure.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>extraBuildCommandsMulti</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Like <literal>extraBuildCommands</literal>, but executed only on multilib
      architectures.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>extraOutputsToInstall</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Additional derivation outputs to be linked for both target and
      multi-architecture packages.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>extraInstallCommands</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Additional commands to be executed for finalizing the derivation with
      runner script.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>runScript</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A command that would be executed inside the sandbox and passed all the
      command line arguments. It defaults to <literal>bash</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   One can create a simple environment using a <literal>shell.nix</literal>
   like that:
  </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
{ pkgs ? import <nixpkgs> {} }:

(pkgs.buildFHSUserEnv {
  name = "simple-x11-env";
  targetPkgs = pkgs: (with pkgs;
    [ udev
      alsaLib
    ]) ++ (with pkgs.xorg;
    [ libX11
      libXcursor
      libXrandr
    ]);
  multiPkgs = pkgs: (with pkgs;
    [ udev
      alsaLib
    ]);
  runScript = "bash";
}).env
]]></programlisting>

  <para>
   Running <literal>nix-shell</literal> would then drop you into a shell with
   these libraries and binaries available. You can use this to run
   closed-source applications which expect FHS structure without hassles:
   simply change <literal>runScript</literal> to the application path, e.g.
   <filename>./bin/start.sh</filename> -- relative paths are supported.
  </para>
 </section>
 <xi:include href="shell.section.xml" />
 <section xml:id="sec-pkgs-dockerTools">
  <title>pkgs.dockerTools</title>

  <para>
   <varname>pkgs.dockerTools</varname> is a set of functions for creating and
   manipulating Docker images according to the
   <link xlink:href="https://github.com/moby/moby/blob/master/image/spec/v1.2.md#docker-image-specification-v120">
   Docker Image Specification v1.2.0 </link>. Docker itself is not used to
   perform any of the operations done by these functions.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <para>
    The <varname>dockerTools</varname> API is unstable and may be subject to
    backwards-incompatible changes in the future.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <section xml:id="ssec-pkgs-dockerTools-buildImage">
   <title>buildImage</title>

   <para>
    This function is analogous to the <command>docker build</command> command,
    in that can used to build a Docker-compatible repository tarball containing
    a single image with one or multiple layers. As such, the result is suitable
    for being loaded in Docker with <command>docker load</command>.
   </para>

   <para>
    The parameters of <varname>buildImage</varname> with relative example
    values are described below:
   </para>

   <example xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage'>
    <title>Docker build</title>
<programlisting>
  buildImage {
    name = "redis"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-1' />
    tag = "latest"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-2' />

    fromImage = someBaseImage; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-3' />
    fromImageName = null; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-4' />
    fromImageTag = "latest"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-5' />

    contents = pkgs.redis; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-6' />
    runAsRoot = '' <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-runAsRoot' />
      #!${stdenv.shell}
      mkdir -p /data
    '';

    config = { <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-8' />
      Cmd = [ "/bin/redis-server" ];
      WorkingDir = "/data";
      Volumes = {
        "/data" = {};
      };
    };
  }
  </programlisting>
   </example>

   <para>
    The above example will build a Docker image <literal>redis/latest</literal>
    from the given base image. Loading and running this image in Docker results
    in <literal>redis-server</literal> being started automatically.
   </para>

   <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-1'>
     <para>
      <varname>name</varname> specifies the name of the resulting image. This
      is the only required argument for <varname>buildImage</varname>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-2'>
     <para>
      <varname>tag</varname> specifies the tag of the resulting image. By
      default it's <literal>null</literal>, which indicates that the nix output
      hash will be used as tag.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-3'>
     <para>
      <varname>fromImage</varname> is the repository tarball containing the
      base image. It must be a valid Docker image, such as exported by
      <command>docker save</command>. By default it's <literal>null</literal>,
      which can be seen as equivalent to <literal>FROM scratch</literal> of a
      <filename>Dockerfile</filename>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-4'>
     <para>
      <varname>fromImageName</varname> can be used to further specify the base
      image within the repository, in case it contains multiple images. By
      default it's <literal>null</literal>, in which case
      <varname>buildImage</varname> will peek the first image available in the
      repository.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-5'>
     <para>
      <varname>fromImageTag</varname> can be used to further specify the tag of
      the base image within the repository, in case an image contains multiple
      tags. By default it's <literal>null</literal>, in which case
      <varname>buildImage</varname> will peek the first tag available for the
      base image.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-6'>
     <para>
      <varname>contents</varname> is a derivation that will be copied in the
      new layer of the resulting image. This can be similarly seen as
      <command>ADD contents/ /</command> in a <filename>Dockerfile</filename>.
      By default it's <literal>null</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-runAsRoot'>
     <para>
      <varname>runAsRoot</varname> is a bash script that will run as root in an
      environment that overlays the existing layers of the base image with the
      new resulting layer, including the previously copied
      <varname>contents</varname> derivation. This can be similarly seen as
      <command>RUN ...</command> in a <filename>Dockerfile</filename>.
      <note>
       <para>
        Using this parameter requires the <literal>kvm</literal> device to be
        available.
       </para>
      </note>
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-8'>
     <para>
      <varname>config</varname> is used to specify the configuration of the
      containers that will be started off the built image in Docker. The
      available options are listed in the
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/moby/moby/blob/master/image/spec/v1.2.md#image-json-field-descriptions">
      Docker Image Specification v1.2.0 </link>.
     </para>
    </callout>
   </calloutlist>

   <para>
    After the new layer has been created, its closure (to which
    <varname>contents</varname>, <varname>config</varname> and
    <varname>runAsRoot</varname> contribute) will be copied in the layer
    itself. Only new dependencies that are not already in the existing layers
    will be copied.
   </para>

   <para>
    At the end of the process, only one new single layer will be produced and
    added to the resulting image.
   </para>

   <para>
    The resulting repository will only list the single image
    <varname>image/tag</varname>. In the case of
    <xref linkend='ex-dockerTools-buildImage'/> it would be
    <varname>redis/latest</varname>.
   </para>

   <para>
    It is possible to inspect the arguments with which an image was built using
    its <varname>buildArgs</varname> attribute.
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     If you see errors similar to <literal>getProtocolByName: does not exist
     (no such protocol name: tcp)</literal> you may need to add
     <literal>pkgs.iana-etc</literal> to <varname>contents</varname>.
    </para>
   </note>

   <note>
    <para>
     If you see errors similar to <literal>Error_Protocol ("certificate has
     unknown CA",True,UnknownCa)</literal> you may need to add
     <literal>pkgs.cacert</literal> to <varname>contents</varname>.
    </para>
   </note>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ssec-pkgs-dockerTools-fetchFromRegistry">
   <title>pullImage</title>

   <para>
    This function is analogous to the <command>docker pull</command> command,
    in that can be used to pull a Docker image from a Docker registry. By
    default <link xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/">Docker Hub</link> is
    used to pull images.
   </para>

   <para>
    Its parameters are described in the example below:
   </para>

   <example xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage'>
    <title>Docker pull</title>
<programlisting>
  pullImage {
    imageName = "nixos/nix"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-1' />
    imageDigest = "sha256:20d9485b25ecfd89204e843a962c1bd70e9cc6858d65d7f5fadc340246e2116b"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-2' />
    finalImageTag = "1.11";  <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-3' />
    sha256 = "0mqjy3zq2v6rrhizgb9nvhczl87lcfphq9601wcprdika2jz7qh8"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-4' />
    os = "linux"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-5' />
    arch = "x86_64"; <co xml:id='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-6' />
  }
  </programlisting>
   </example>

   <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-1'>
     <para>
      <varname>imageName</varname> specifies the name of the image to be
      downloaded, which can also include the registry namespace (e.g.
      <literal>nixos</literal>). This argument is required.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-2'>
     <para>
      <varname>imageDigest</varname> specifies the digest of the image to be
      downloaded. Skopeo can be used to get the digest of an image, with its
      <varname>inspect</varname> subcommand. Since a given
      <varname>imageName</varname> may transparently refer to a manifest list
      of images which support multiple architectures and/or operating systems,
      supply the `--override-os` and `--override-arch` arguments to specify
      exactly which image you want. By default it will match the OS and
      architecture of the host the command is run on.
<programlisting>
  $ nix-shell --packages skopeo jq --command "skopeo --override-os linux --override-arch x86_64 inspect docker://docker.io/nixos/nix:1.11 | jq -r '.Digest'"
  sha256:20d9485b25ecfd89204e843a962c1bd70e9cc6858d65d7f5fadc340246e2116b
  </programlisting>
      This argument is required.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-3'>
     <para>
      <varname>finalImageTag</varname>, if specified, this is the tag of the
      image to be created. Note it is never used to fetch the image since we
      prefer to rely on the immutable digest ID. By default it's
      <literal>latest</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-4'>
     <para>
      <varname>sha256</varname> is the checksum of the whole fetched image.
      This argument is required.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-5'>
     <para>
      <varname>os</varname>, if specified, is the operating system of the
      fetched image. By default it's <literal>linux</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs='ex-dockerTools-pullImage-6'>
     <para>
      <varname>arch</varname>, if specified, is the cpu architecture of the
      fetched image. By default it's <literal>x86_64</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
   </calloutlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ssec-pkgs-dockerTools-exportImage">
   <title>exportImage</title>

   <para>
    This function is analogous to the <command>docker export</command> command,
    in that can used to flatten a Docker image that contains multiple layers.
    It is in fact the result of the merge of all the layers of the image. As
    such, the result is suitable for being imported in Docker with
    <command>docker import</command>.
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     Using this function requires the <literal>kvm</literal> device to be
     available.
    </para>
   </note>

   <para>
    The parameters of <varname>exportImage</varname> are the following:
   </para>

   <example xml:id='ex-dockerTools-exportImage'>
    <title>Docker export</title>
<programlisting>
  exportImage {
    fromImage = someLayeredImage;
    fromImageName = null;
    fromImageTag = null;

    name = someLayeredImage.name;
  }
  </programlisting>
   </example>

   <para>
    The parameters relative to the base image have the same synopsis as
    described in <xref linkend='ssec-pkgs-dockerTools-buildImage'/>, except
    that <varname>fromImage</varname> is the only required argument in this
    case.
   </para>

   <para>
    The <varname>name</varname> argument is the name of the derivation output,
    which defaults to <varname>fromImage.name</varname>.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ssec-pkgs-dockerTools-shadowSetup">
   <title>shadowSetup</title>

   <para>
    This constant string is a helper for setting up the base files for managing
    users and groups, only if such files don't exist already. It is suitable
    for being used in a <varname>runAsRoot</varname>
    <xref linkend='ex-dockerTools-buildImage-runAsRoot'/> script for cases like
    in the example below:
   </para>

   <example xml:id='ex-dockerTools-shadowSetup'>
    <title>Shadow base files</title>
<programlisting>
  buildImage {
    name = "shadow-basic";

    runAsRoot = ''
      #!${stdenv.shell}
      ${shadowSetup}
      groupadd -r redis
      useradd -r -g redis redis
      mkdir /data
      chown redis:redis /data
    '';
  }
  </programlisting>
   </example>

   <para>
    Creating base files like <literal>/etc/passwd</literal> or
    <literal>/etc/login.defs</literal> are necessary for shadow-utils to
    manipulate users and groups.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
</chapter>
