<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="users-guide-to-the-haskell-infrastructure">

<title>User's Guide to the Haskell Infrastructure</title>

<section xml:id="how-to-install-haskell-packages">
  <title>How to install Haskell packages</title>
  <para>
    Nixpkgs distributes build instructions for all Haskell packages
    registered on
    <link xlink:href="http://hackage.haskell.org/">Hackage</link>, but
    strangely enough normal Nix package lookups don't seem to discover
    any of them:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -qa cabal-install
error: selector ‘cabal-install’ matches no derivations

$ nix-env -i ghc
error: selector ‘ghc’ matches no derivations
</programlisting>
  <para>
    The Haskell package set is not registered in the top-level namespace
    because it is <emphasis>huge</emphasis>. If all Haskell packages
    were visible to these commands, then name-based search/install
    operations would be much slower than they are now. We avoided that
    by keeping all Haskell-related packages in a separate attribute set
    called <literal>haskellPackages</literal>, which the following
    command will list:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -qaP -A haskellPackages
haskellPackages.a50         a50-0.5
haskellPackages.abacate     haskell-abacate-0.0.0.0
haskellPackages.abcBridge   haskell-abcBridge-0.12
haskellPackages.afv         afv-0.1.1
haskellPackages.alex        alex-3.1.4
haskellPackages.Allure      Allure-0.4.101.1
haskellPackages.alms        alms-0.6.7
[... some 8000 entries omitted  ...]
</programlisting>
  <para>
    To install any of those packages into your profile, refer to them by
    their attribute path (first column):
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -iA haskellPackages.Allure ...
</programlisting>
  <para>
    The attribute path of any Haskell packages corresponds to the name
    of that particular package on Hackage: the package
    <literal>cabal-install</literal> has the attribute
    <literal>haskellPackages.cabal-install</literal>, and so on.
    (Actually, this convention causes trouble with packages like
    <literal>3dmodels</literal> and <literal>4Blocks</literal>, because
    these names are invalid identifiers in the Nix language. The issue
    of how to deal with these rare corner cases is currently
    unresolved.)
  </para>
  <para>
    Haskell packages who's Nix name (second column) begins with a
    <literal>haskell-</literal> prefix are packages that provide a
    library whereas packages without that prefix provide just
    executables. Libraries may provide executables too, though: the
    package <literal>haskell-pandoc</literal>, for example, installs
    both a library and an application. You can install and use Haskell
    executables just like any other program in Nixpkgs, but using
    Haskell libraries for development is a bit trickier and we'll
    address that subject in great detail in section
    <link linkend="how-to-create-a-development-environment">How to
    create a development environment</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    Attribute paths are deterministic inside of Nixpkgs, but the path
    necessary to reach Nixpkgs varies from system to system. We dodged
    that problem by giving <literal>nix-env</literal> an explicit
    <literal>-f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot;</literal> parameter, but if
    you call <literal>nix-env</literal> without that flag, then chances
    are the invocation fails:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -iA haskellPackages.cabal-install
error: attribute ‘haskellPackages’ in selection path
       ‘haskellPackages.cabal-install’ not found
</programlisting>
  <para>
    On NixOS, for example, Nixpkgs does <emphasis>not</emphasis> exist
    in the top-level namespace by default. To figure out the proper
    attribute path, it's easiest to query for the path of a well-known
    Nixpkgs package, i.e.:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -qaP coreutils
nixos.coreutils  coreutils-8.23
</programlisting>
  <para>
    If your system responds like that (most NixOS installatios will),
    then the attribute path to <literal>haskellPackages</literal> is
    <literal>nixos.haskellPackages</literal>. Thus, if you want to
    use <literal>nix-env</literal> without giving an explicit
    <literal>-f</literal> flag, then that's the way to do it:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -qaP -A nixos.haskellPackages
$ nix-env -iA nixos.haskellPackages.cabal-install
</programlisting>
  <para>
    Our current default compiler is GHC 7.10.x and the
    <literal>haskellPackages</literal> set contains packages built with
    that particular version. Nixpkgs contains the latest major release
    of every GHC since 6.10.4, however, and there is a whole family of
    package sets available that defines Hackage packages built with each
    of those compilers, too:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -qaP -A haskell.packages.ghc6123
$ nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -qaP -A haskell.packages.ghc763
</programlisting>
  <para>
    The name <literal>haskellPackages</literal> is really just a synonym
    for <literal>haskell.packages.ghc7101</literal>, because we prefer
    that package set internally and recommend it to our users as their
    default choice, but ultimately you are free to compile your Haskell
    packages with any GHC version you please. The following command
    displays the complete list of available compilers:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -qaP -A haskell.compiler
haskell.compiler.ghc6104        ghc-6.10.4
haskell.compiler.ghc6123        ghc-6.12.3
haskell.compiler.ghc704         ghc-7.0.4
haskell.compiler.ghc722         ghc-7.2.2
haskell.compiler.ghc742         ghc-7.4.2
haskell.compiler.ghc763         ghc-7.6.3
haskell.compiler.ghc784         ghc-7.8.4
haskell.compiler.ghc7101        ghc-7.10.1
haskell.compiler.ghcHEAD        ghc-7.11.20150402
haskell.compiler.ghcNokinds     ghc-nokinds-7.11.20150704
haskell.compiler.ghcjs          ghcjs-0.1.0
haskell.compiler.jhc            jhc-0.8.2
haskell.compiler.uhc            uhc-1.1.9.0
</programlisting>
  <para>
    We have no package sets for <literal>jhc</literal> or
    <literal>uhc</literal> yet, unfortunately, but for every version of
    GHC listed above, there exists a package set based on that compiler.
    Also, the attributes <literal>haskell.compiler.ghcXYC</literal> and
    <literal>haskell.packages.ghcXYC.ghc</literal> are synonymous for
    the sake of convenience.
  </para>
</section>
<section xml:id="how-to-create-a-development-environment">
  <title>How to create a development environment</title>
  <section xml:id="how-to-install-a-compiler">
    <title>How to install a compiler</title>
    <para>
      A simple development environment consists of a Haskell compiler
      and the tool <literal>cabal-install</literal>, and we saw in
      section <link linkend="how-to-install-haskell-packages">How to
      install Haskell packages</link> how you can install those programs
      into your user profile:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -iA haskellPackages.ghc haskellPackages.cabal-install
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Instead of the default package set
      <literal>haskellPackages</literal>, you can also use the more
      precise name <literal>haskell.compiler.ghc7101</literal>, which
      has the advantage that it refers to the same GHC version
      regardless of what Nixpkgs considers &quot;default&quot; at any
      given time.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once you've made those tools available in
      <literal>$PATH</literal>, it's possible to build Hackage packages
      the same way people without access to Nix do it all the time:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cabal get lens-4.11 &amp;&amp; cd lens-4.11
$ cabal install -j --dependencies-only
$ cabal configure
$ cabal build
</programlisting>
    <para>
      If you enjoy working with Cabal sandboxes, then that's entirely
      possible too: just execute the command
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cabal sandbox init
</programlisting>
    <para>
      before installing the required dependencies.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>nix-shell</literal> utility makes it easy to switch
      to a different compiler version; just enter the Nix shell
      environment with the command
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-shell -p haskell.compiler.ghc784
</programlisting>
    <para>
      to bring GHC 7.8.4 into <literal>$PATH</literal>. Re-running
      <literal>cabal configure</literal> switches your build to use that
      compiler instead. If you're working on a project that doesn't
      depend on any additional system libraries outside of GHC, then
      it's sufficient even to run the <literal>cabal configure</literal>
      command inside of the shell:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-shell -p haskell.compiler.ghc784 --command &quot;cabal configure&quot;
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Afterwards, all other commands like <literal>cabal build</literal>
      work just fine in any shell environment, because the configure
      phase recorded the absolute paths to all required tools like GHC
      in its build configuration inside of the <literal>dist/</literal>
      directory. Please note, however, that
      <literal>nix-collect-garbage</literal> can break such an
      environment because the Nix store paths created by
      <literal>nix-shell</literal> aren't &quot;alive&quot; anymore once
      <literal>nix-shell</literal> has terminated. If you find that your
      Haskell builds no longer work after garbage collection, then
      you'll have to re-run <literal>cabal configure</literal> inside of
      a new <literal>nix-shell</literal> environment.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="how-to-install-a-compiler-with-libraries">
    <title>How to install a compiler with libraries</title>
    <para>
      GHC expects to find all installed libraries inside of its own
      <literal>lib</literal> directory. This approach works fine on
      traditional Unix systems, but it doesn't work for Nix, because
      GHC's store path is immutable once it's built. We cannot install
      additional libraries into that location. As a consequence, our
      copies of GHC don't know any packages except their own core
      libraries, like <literal>base</literal>,
      <literal>containers</literal>, <literal>Cabal</literal>, etc.
    </para>
    <para>
      We can register additional libraries to GHC, however, using a
      special build function called <literal>ghcWithPackages</literal>.
      That function expects one argument: a function that maps from an
      attribute set of Haskell packages to a list of packages, which
      determines the libraries known to that particular version of GHC.
      For example, the Nix expression
      <literal>ghcWithPackages (pkgs: [pkgs.mtl])</literal> generates a
      copy of GHC that has the <literal>mtl</literal> library registered
      in addition to its normal core packages:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-shell -p &quot;haskellPackages.ghcWithPackages (pkgs: [pkgs.mtl])&quot;

[nix-shell:~]$ ghc-pkg list mtl
/nix/store/zy79...-ghc-7.10.1/lib/ghc-7.10.1/package.conf.d:
    mtl-2.2.1
</programlisting>
    <para>
      This function allows users to define their own development
      environment by means of an override. After adding the following
      snippet to <literal>~/.nixpkgs/config.nix</literal>,
    </para>
    <programlisting>
{
  packageOverrides = super: let self = super.pkgs; in
  {
    myHaskellEnv = self.haskell.packages.ghc7101.ghcWithPackages
                     (haskellPackages: with haskellPackages; [
                       # libraries
                       arrows async cgi criterion
                       # tools
                       cabal-install haskintex
                     ]);
  };
}
</programlisting>
    <para>
      it's possible to install that compiler with
      <literal>nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -iA myHaskellEnv</literal>.
      If you'd like to switch that development environment to a
      different version of GHC, just replace the
      <literal>ghc7101</literal> bit in the previous definition with the
      appropriate name. Of course, it's also possible to define any
      number of these development environments! (You can't install two
      of them into the same profile at the same time, though, because
      that would result in file conflicts.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The generated <literal>ghc</literal> program is a wrapper script
      that re-directs the real GHC executable to use a new
      <literal>lib</literal> directory --- one that we specifically
      constructed to contain all those packages the user requested:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cat $(type -p ghc)
#! /nix/store/xlxj...-bash-4.3-p33/bin/bash -e
export NIX_GHC=/nix/store/19sm...-ghc-7.10.1/bin/ghc
export NIX_GHCPKG=/nix/store/19sm...-ghc-7.10.1/bin/ghc-pkg
export NIX_GHC_DOCDIR=/nix/store/19sm...-ghc-7.10.1/share/doc/ghc/html
export NIX_GHC_LIBDIR=/nix/store/19sm...-ghc-7.10.1/lib/ghc-7.10.1
exec /nix/store/j50p...-ghc-7.10.1/bin/ghc &quot;-B$NIX_GHC_LIBDIR&quot; &quot;$@&quot;
</programlisting>
    <para>
      The variables <literal>$NIX_GHC</literal>,
      <literal>$NIX_GHCPKG</literal>, etc. point to the
      <emphasis>new</emphasis> store path
      <literal>ghcWithPackages</literal> constructed specifically for
      this environment. The last line of the wrapper script then
      executes the real <literal>ghc</literal>, but passes the path to
      the new <literal>lib</literal> directory using GHC's
      <literal>-B</literal> flag.
    </para>
    <para>
      The purpose of those environment variables is to work around an
      impurity in the popular
      <link xlink:href="http://hackage.haskell.org/package/ghc-paths">ghc-paths</link>
      library. That library promises to give its users access to GHC's
      installation paths. Only, the library can't possible know that
      path when it's compiled, because the path GHC considers its own is
      determined only much later, when the user configures it through
      <literal>ghcWithPackages</literal>. So we
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/blob/master/pkgs/development/haskell-modules/ghc-paths-nix.patch">patched
      ghc-paths</link> to return the paths found in those environment
      variables at run-time rather than trying to guess them at
      compile-time.
    </para>
    <para>
      To make sure that mechanism works properly all the time, we
      recommend that you set those variables to meaningful values in
      your shell environment, too, i.e. by adding the following code to
      your <literal>~/.bashrc</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
if type &gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1 -p ghc; then
  eval &quot;$(egrep ^export &quot;$(type -p ghc)&quot;)&quot;
fi
</programlisting>
    <para>
      If you are certain that you'll use only one GHC environment which
      is located in your user profile, then you can use the following
      code, too, which has the advantage that it doesn't contain any
      paths from the Nix store, i.e. those settings always remain valid
      even if a <literal>nix-env -u</literal> operation updates the GHC
      environment in your profile:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
if [ -e ~/.nix-profile/bin/ghc ]; then
  export NIX_GHC=&quot;$HOME/.nix-profile/bin/ghc&quot;
  export NIX_GHCPKG=&quot;$HOME/.nix-profile/bin/ghc-pkg&quot;
  export NIX_GHC_DOCDIR=&quot;$HOME/.nix-profile/share/doc/ghc/html&quot;
  export NIX_GHC_LIBDIR=&quot;$HOME/.nix-profile/lib/ghc-$($NIX_GHC --numeric-version)&quot;
fi
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="how-to-create-ad-hoc-environments-for-nix-shell">
    <title>How to create ad hoc environments for
    <literal>nix-shell</literal></title>
    <para>
      The easiest way to create an ad hoc development environment is to
      run <literal>nix-shell</literal> with the appropriate GHC
      environment given on the command-line:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
nix-shell -p &quot;haskellPackages.ghcWithPackages (pkgs: with pkgs; [mtl pandoc])&quot;
</programlisting>
    <para>
      For more sophisticated use-cases, however, it's more convenient to
      save the desired configuration in a file called
      <literal>shell.nix</literal> that looks like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
{ nixpkgs ? import &lt;nixpkgs&gt; {}, compiler ? &quot;ghc7101&quot; }:
let
  inherit (nixpkgs) pkgs;
  ghc = pkgs.haskell.packages.${compiler}.ghcWithPackages (ps: with ps; [
          monad-par mtl
        ]);
in
pkgs.stdenv.mkDerivation {
  name = &quot;my-haskell-env-0&quot;;
  buildInputs = [ ghc ];
  shellHook = &quot;eval $(egrep ^export ${ghc}/bin/ghc)&quot;;
}
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Now run <literal>nix-shell</literal> --- or even
      <literal>nix-shell --pure</literal> --- to enter a shell
      environment that has the appropriate compiler in
      <literal>$PATH</literal>. If you use <literal>--pure</literal>,
      then add all other packages that your development environment
      needs into the <literal>buildInputs</literal> attribute. If you'd
      like to switch to a different compiler version, then pass an
      appropriate <literal>compiler</literal> argument to the
      expression, i.e.
      <literal>nix-shell --argstr compiler ghc784</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you need such an environment because you'd like to compile a
      Hackage package outside of Nix --- i.e. because you're hacking on
      the latest version from Git ---, then the package set provides
      suitable nix-shell environments for you already! Every Haskell
      package has an <literal>env</literal> attribute that provides a
      shell environment suitable for compiling that particular package.
      If you'd like to hack the <literal>lens</literal> library, for
      example, then you just have to check out the source code and enter
      the appropriate environment:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
  $ cabal get lens-4.11 &amp;&amp; cd lens-4.11
  Downloading lens-4.11...
  Unpacking to lens-4.11/

  $ nix-shell &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -A haskellPackages.lens.env
  [nix-shell:/tmp/lens-4.11]$
</programlisting>
    <para>
      At point, you can run <literal>cabal configure</literal>,
      <literal>cabal build</literal>, and all the other development
      commands. Note that you need <literal>cabal-install</literal>
      installed in your <literal>$PATH</literal> already to use it here
      --- the <literal>nix-shell</literal> environment does not provide
      it.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
<section xml:id="how-to-create-nix-builds-for-your-own-private-haskell-packages">
  <title>How to create Nix builds for your own private Haskell
  packages</title>
  <para>
    If your own Haskell packages have build instructions for Cabal, then
    you can convert those automatically into build instructions for Nix
    using the <literal>cabal2nix</literal> utility, which you can
    install into your profile by running
    <literal>nix-env -i cabal2nix</literal>.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="how-to-build-a-stand-alone-project">
    <title>How to build a stand-alone project</title>
    <para>
      For example, let's assume that you're working on a private project
      called <literal>foo</literal>. To generate a Nix build expression
      for it, change into the project's top-level directory and run the
      command:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cabal2nix . &gt;foo.nix
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Then write the following snippet into a file called
      <literal>default.nix</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
{ nixpkgs ? import &lt;nixpkgs&gt; {}, compiler ? &quot;ghc7101&quot; }:
nixpkgs.pkgs.haskell.packages.${compiler}.callPackage ./foo.nix { }
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Finally, store the following code in a file called
      <literal>shell.nix</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
{ nixpkgs ? import &lt;nixpkgs&gt; {}, compiler ? &quot;ghc7101&quot; }:
(import ./default.nix { inherit nixpkgs compiler; }).env
</programlisting>
    <para>
      At this point, you can run <literal>nix-build</literal> to have
      Nix compile your project and install it into a Nix store path. The
      local directory will contain a symlink called
      <literal>result</literal> after <literal>nix-build</literal>
      returns that points into that location. Of course, passing the
      flag <literal>--argstr compiler ghc763</literal> allows switching
      the build to any version of GHC currently supported.
    </para>
    <para>
      Furthermore, you can call <literal>nix-shell</literal> to enter an
      interactive development environment in which you can use
      <literal>cabal configure</literal> and
      <literal>cabal build</literal> to develop your code. That
      environment will automatically contain a proper GHC derivation
      with all the required libraries registered as well as all the
      system-level libraries your package might need.
    </para>
    <para>
      If your package does not depend on any system-level libraries,
      then it's sufficient to run
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-shell --command &quot;cabal configure&quot;
</programlisting>
    <para>
      once to set up your build. <literal>cabal-install</literal>
      determines the absolute paths to all resources required for the
      build and writes them into a config file in the
      <literal>dist/</literal> directory. Once that's done, you can run
      <literal>cabal build</literal> and any other command for that
      project even outside of the <literal>nix-shell</literal>
      environment. This feature is particularly nice for those of us who
      like to edit their code with an IDE, like Emacs'
      <literal>haskell-mode</literal>, because it's not necessary to
      start Emacs inside of nix-shell just to make it find out the
      necessary settings for building the project;
      <literal>cabal-install</literal> has already done that for us.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you want to do some quick-and-dirty hacking and don't want to
      bother setting up a <literal>default.nix</literal> and
      <literal>shell.nix</literal> file manually, then you can use the
      <literal>--shell</literal> flag offered by
      <literal>cabal2nix</literal> to have it generate a stand-alone
      <literal>nix-shell</literal> environment for you. With that
      feature, running
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cabal2nix --shell . &gt;shell.nix
$ nix-shell --command &quot;cabal configure&quot;
</programlisting>
    <para>
      is usually enough to set up a build environment for any given
      Haskell package. You can even use that generated file to run
      <literal>nix-build</literal>, too:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-build shell.nix
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="how-to-build-projects-that-depend-on-each-other">
    <title>How to build projects that depend on each other</title>
    <para>
      If you have multiple private Haskell packages that depend on each
      other, then you'll have to register those packages in the Nixpkgs
      set to make them visible for the dependency resolution performed
      by <literal>callPackage</literal>. First of all, change into each
      of your projects top-level directories and generate a
      <literal>default.nix</literal> file with
      <literal>cabal2nix</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cd ~/src/foo &amp;&amp; cabal2nix . &gt;default.nix
$ cd ~/src/bar &amp;&amp; cabal2nix . &gt;default.nix
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Then edit your <literal>~/.nixpkgs/config.nix</literal> file to
      register those builds in the default Haskell package set:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
  {
    packageOverrides = super: let self = super.pkgs; in
    {
      haskellPackages = super.haskellPackages.override {
        overrides = self: super: {
          foo = self.callPackage ../src/foo {};
          bar = self.callPackage ../src/bar {};
        };
      };
    };
  }
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Once that's accomplished,
      <literal>nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -qA haskellPackages</literal>
      will show your packages like any other package from Hackage, and
      you can build them
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-build &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -A haskellPackages.foo
</programlisting>
    <para>
      or enter an interactive shell environment suitable for building
      them:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ nix-shell &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -A haskellPackages.bar.env
</programlisting>
  </section>
</section>
<section xml:id="miscellaneous-topics">
  <title>Miscellaneous Topics</title>
  <section xml:id="how-to-build-with-profiling-enabled">
    <title>How to build with profiling enabled</title>
    <para>
      Every Haskell package set takes a function called
      <literal>overrides</literal> that you can use to manipulate the
      package as much as you please. One useful application of this
      feature is to replace the default <literal>mkDerivation</literal>
      function with one that enables library profiling for all packages.
      To accomplish that, add configure the following snippet in your
      <literal>~/.nixpkgs/config.nix</literal> file:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
{
  packageOverrides = super: let self = super.pkgs; in
  {
    profiledHaskellPackages = self.haskellPackages.override {
      overrides = self: super: {
        mkDerivation = args: super.mkDerivation (args // {
          enableLibraryProfiling = true;
        });
      };
    };
  };
}
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="how-to-override-package-versions-in-a-compiler-specific-package-set">
    <title>How to override package versions in a compiler-specific
    package set</title>
    <para>
      Nixpkgs provides the latest version of
      <link xlink:href="http://hackage.haskell.org/package/ghc-events"><literal>ghc-events</literal></link>,
      which is 0.4.4.0 at the time of this writing. This is fine for
      users of GHC 7.10.x, but GHC 7.8.4 cannot compile that binary.
      Now, one way to solve that problem is to register an older version
      of <literal>ghc-events</literal> in the 7.8.x-specific package
      set. The first step is to generate Nix build instructions with
      <literal>cabal2nix</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cabal2nix cabal://ghc-events-0.4.3.0 &gt;~/.nixpkgs/ghc-events-0.4.3.0.nix
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Then add the override in <literal>~/.nixpkgs/config.nix</literal>:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
{
  packageOverrides = super: let self = super.pkgs; in
  {
    haskell = super.haskell // {
      packages = super.haskell.packages // {
        ghc784 = super.haskell.packages.ghc784.override {
          overrides = self: super: {
            ghc-events = self.callPackage ./ghc-events-0.4.3.0.nix {};
          };
        };
      };
    };
  };
}
</programlisting>
    <para>
      This code is a little crazy, no doubt, but it's necessary because
      the intuitive version
    </para>
    <programlisting>
haskell.packages.ghc784 = super.haskell.packages.ghc784.override {
  overrides = self: super: {
    ghc-events = self.callPackage ./ghc-events-0.4.3.0.nix {};
  };
};
</programlisting>
    <para>
      doesn't do what we want it to: that code replaces the
      <literal>haskell</literal> package set in Nixpkgs with one that
      contains only one entry,<literal>packages</literal>, which
      contains only one entry <literal>ghc784</literal>. This override
      loses the <literal>haskell.compiler</literal> set, and it loses
      the <literal>haskell.packages.ghcXYZ</literal> sets for all
      compilers but GHC 7.8.4. To avoid that problem, we have to perform
      the convoluted little dance from above, iterating over each step
      in hierarchy.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once it's accomplished, however, we can install a variant of
      <literal>ghc-events</literal> that's compiled with GHC 7.8.4:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
nix-env -f &quot;&lt;nixpkgs&gt;&quot; -iA haskell.packages.ghc784.ghc-events
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Unfortunately, it turns out that this build fails again while
      executing the test suite! Apparently, the release archive on
      Hackage is missing some data files that the test suite requires,
      so we cannot run it. We accomplish that by re-generating the Nix
      expression with the <literal>--no-check</literal> flag:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
$ cabal2nix --no-check cabal://ghc-events-0.4.3.0 &gt;~/.nixpkgs/ghc-events-0.4.3.0.nix
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Now the builds succeeds.
    </para>
    <para>
      Of course, in the concrete example of
      <literal>ghc-events</literal> this whole exercise is not an ideal
      solution, because <literal>ghc-events</literal> can analyze the
      output emitted by any version of GHC later than 6.12 regardless of
      the compiler version that was used to build the `ghc-events'
      executable, so strictly speaking there's no reason to prefer one
      built with GHC 7.8.x in the first place. However, for users who
      cannot use GHC 7.10.x at all for some reason, the approach of
      downgrading to an older version might be useful.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="how-to-recover-from-ghcs-infamous-non-deterministic-library-id-bug">
    <title>How to recover from GHC's infamous non-deterministic library
    ID bug</title>
    <para>
      GHC and distributed build farms don't get along well:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
https://ghc.haskell.org/trac/ghc/ticket/4012
</programlisting>
    <para>
      When you see an error like this one
    </para>
    <programlisting>
package foo-0.7.1.0 is broken due to missing package
text-1.2.0.4-98506efb1b9ada233bb5c2b2db516d91
</programlisting>
    <para>
      then you have to download and re-install <literal>foo</literal>
      and all its dependents from scratch:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
# nix-store -q --referrers /nix/store/*-haskell-text-1.2.0.4 \
  | xargs -L 1 nix-store --repair-path --option binary-caches http://hydra.nixos.org
</programlisting>
    <para>
      If you're using additional Hydra servers other than
      <literal>hydra.nixos.org</literal>, then it might be necessary to
      purge the local caches that store data from those machines to
      disable these binary channels for the duration of the previous
      command, i.e. by running:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
rm /nix/var/nix/binary-cache-v3.sqlite
rm /nix/var/nix/manifests/*
rm /nix/var/nix/channel-cache/*
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="builds-on-darwin-fail-with-math.h-not-found">
    <title>Builds on Darwin fail with <literal>math.h</literal> not
    found</title>
    <para>
      Users of GHC on Darwin have occasionally reported that builds
      fail, because the compiler complains about a missing include file:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
fatal error: 'math.h' file not found
</programlisting>
    <para>
      The issue has been discussed at length in
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/issues/6390">ticket
      6390</link>, and so far no good solution has been proposed. As a
      work-around, users who run into this problem can configure the
      environment variables
    </para>
    <programlisting>
export NIX_CFLAGS_COMPILE=&quot;-idirafter /usr/include&quot;
export NIX_CFLAGS_LINK=&quot;-L/usr/lib&quot;
</programlisting>
    <para>
      in their <literal>~/.bashrc</literal> file to avoid the compiler
      error.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

</chapter>
