<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-release-23.05">
  <title>Release 23.05 (“Stoat”, 2023.05/??)</title>
  <para>
    Support is planned until the end of December 2023, handing over to
    23.11.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="sec-release-23.05-highlights">
    <title>Highlights</title>
    <para>
      In addition to numerous new and upgraded packages, this release
      has the following highlights:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create the first release note entry in this section!
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-release-23.05-new-services">
    <title>New Services</title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create the first release note entry in this section!
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-release-23.05-incompatibilities">
    <title>Backward Incompatibilities</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>carnix</literal> and <literal>cratesIO</literal> has
          been removed due to being unmaintained, use alternatives such
          as
          <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nix-community/naersk">naersk</link>
          and
          <link xlink:href="https://github.com/kolloch/crate2nix">crate2nix</link>
          instead.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The EC2 image module no longer fetches instance metadata in
          stage-1. This results in a significantly smaller initramfs,
          since network drivers no longer need to be included, and
          faster boots, since metadata fetching can happen in parallel
          with startup of other services. This breaks services which
          rely on metadata being present by the time stage-2 is entered.
          Anything which reads EC2 metadata from
          <literal>/etc/ec2-metadata</literal> should now have an
          <literal>after</literal> dependency on
          <literal>fetch-ec2-metadata.service</literal>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The EC2 image module previously detected and automatically
          mounted ext3-formatted instance store devices and partitions
          in stage-1 (initramfs), storing <literal>/tmp</literal> on the
          first discovered device. This behaviour, which only catered to
          very specific use cases and could not be disabled, has been
          removed. Users relying on this should provide their own
          implementation, and probably use ext4 and perform the mount in
          stage-2.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The EC2 image module previously detected and activated
          swap-formatted instance store devices and partitions in
          stage-1 (initramfs). This behaviour has been removed. Users
          relying on this should provide their own implementation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-release-23.05-notable-changes">
    <title>Other Notable Changes</title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create the first release note entry in this section!
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
