<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-cgroups">
  <title>Control Groups</title>
  <para>
    To keep track of the processes in a running system, systemd uses
    <emphasis>control groups</emphasis> (cgroups). A control group is a
    set of processes used to allocate resources such as CPU, memory or
    I/O bandwidth. There can be multiple control group hierarchies,
    allowing each kind of resource to be managed independently.
  </para>
  <para>
    The command <literal>systemd-cgls</literal> lists all control groups
    in the <literal>systemd</literal> hierarchy, which is what systemd
    uses to keep track of the processes belonging to each service or
    user session:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ systemd-cgls
├─user
│ └─eelco
│   └─c1
│     ├─ 2567 -:0
│     ├─ 2682 kdeinit4: kdeinit4 Running...
│     ├─ ...
│     └─10851 sh -c less -R
└─system
  ├─httpd.service
  │ ├─2444 httpd -f /nix/store/3pyacby5cpr55a03qwbnndizpciwq161-httpd.conf -DNO_DETACH
  │ └─...
  ├─dhcpcd.service
  │ └─2376 dhcpcd --config /nix/store/f8dif8dsi2yaa70n03xir8r653776ka6-dhcpcd.conf
  └─ ...
</programlisting>
  <para>
    Similarly, <literal>systemd-cgls cpu</literal> shows the cgroups in
    the CPU hierarchy, which allows per-cgroup CPU scheduling
    priorities. By default, every systemd service gets its own CPU
    cgroup, while all user sessions are in the top-level CPU cgroup.
    This ensures, for instance, that a thousand run-away processes in
    the <literal>httpd.service</literal> cgroup cannot starve the CPU
    for one process in the <literal>postgresql.service</literal> cgroup.
    (By contrast, it they were in the same cgroup, then the PostgreSQL
    process would get 1/1001 of the cgroup’s CPU time.) You can limit a
    service’s CPU share in <literal>configuration.nix</literal>:
  </para>
  <programlisting language="nix">
systemd.services.httpd.serviceConfig.CPUShares = 512;
</programlisting>
  <para>
    By default, every cgroup has 1024 CPU shares, so this will halve the
    CPU allocation of the <literal>httpd.service</literal> cgroup.
  </para>
  <para>
    There also is a <literal>memory</literal> hierarchy that controls
    memory allocation limits; by default, all processes are in the
    top-level cgroup, so any service or session can exhaust all
    available memory. Per-cgroup memory limits can be specified in
    <literal>configuration.nix</literal>; for instance, to limit
    <literal>httpd.service</literal> to 512 MiB of RAM (excluding swap):
  </para>
  <programlisting language="nix">
systemd.services.httpd.serviceConfig.MemoryLimit = &quot;512M&quot;;
</programlisting>
  <para>
    The command <literal>systemd-cgtop</literal> shows a continuously
    updated list of all cgroups with their CPU and memory usage.
  </para>
</chapter>
