<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="module-services-mjolnir">
 <title>Mjolnir (Matrix Moderation Tool)</title>
 <para>
  This chapter will show you how to set up your own, self-hosted
  <link xlink:href="https://github.com/matrix-org/mjolnir">Mjolnir</link>
  instance.
 </para>
 <para>
  As an all-in-one moderation tool, it can protect your server from
  malicious invites, spam messages, and whatever else you don't want.
  In addition to server-level protection, Mjolnir is great for communities
  wanting to protect their rooms without having to use their personal
  accounts for moderation.
 </para>
 <para>
  The bot by default includes support for bans, redactions, anti-spam,
  server ACLs, room directory changes, room alias transfers, account
  deactivation, room shutdown, and more.
 </para>
 <para>
  See the <link xlink:href="https://github.com/matrix-org/mjolnir#readme">README</link>
  page and the <link xlink:href="https://github.com/matrix-org/mjolnir/blob/main/docs/moderators.md">Moderator's guide</link>
  for additional instructions on how to setup and use Mjolnir.
 </para>
 <para>
  For <link linkend="opt-services.mjolnir.settings">additional settings</link>
  see <link xlink:href="https://github.com/matrix-org/mjolnir/blob/main/config/default.yaml">the default configuration</link>.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="module-services-mjolnir-setup">
  <title>Mjolnir Setup</title>
  <para>
   First create a new Room which will be used as a management room for Mjolnir. In
   this room, Mjolnir will log possible errors and debugging information. You'll
   need to set this Room-ID in <link linkend="opt-services.mjolnir.managementRoom">services.mjolnir.managementRoom</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Next, create a new user for Mjolnir on your homeserver, if not present already.
  </para>
  <para>
   The Mjolnir Matrix user expects to be free of any rate limiting.
   See <link xlink:href="https://github.com/matrix-org/synapse/issues/6286">Synapse #6286</link>
   for an example on how to achieve this.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you want Mjolnir to be able to deactivate users, move room aliases, shutdown rooms, etc.
   you'll need to make the Mjolnir user a Matrix server admin.
  </para>
  <para>
   Now invite the Mjolnir user to the management room.
  </para>
  <para>
   It is recommended to use <link xlink:href="https://github.com/matrix-org/pantalaimon">Pantalaimon</link>,
   so your management room can be encrypted. This also applies if you are looking to moderate an encrypted room.
  </para>
  <para>
   To enable the Pantalaimon E2E Proxy for mjolnir, enable
   <link linkend="opt-services.mjolnir.pantalaimon.enable">services.mjolnir.pantalaimon</link>. This will
   autoconfigure a new Pantalaimon instance, which will connect to the homeserver
   set in <link linkend="opt-services.mjolnir.homeserverUrl">services.mjolnir.homeserverUrl</link> and Mjolnir itself
   will be configured to connect to the new Pantalaimon instance.
  </para>
<programlisting>
{
  services.mjolnir = {
    enable = true;
    homeserverUrl = "https://matrix.domain.tld";
    pantalaimon = {
       enable = true;
       username = "mjolnir";
       passwordFile = "/run/secrets/mjolnir-password";
    };
    protectedRooms = [
      "https://matrix.to/#/!xxx:domain.tld"
    ];
    managementRoom = "!yyy:domain.tld";
  };
}
</programlisting>
 <section xml:id="module-services-mjolnir-setup-ems">
  <title>Element Matrix Services (EMS)</title>
  <para>
   If you are using a managed <link xlink:href="https://ems.element.io/">"Element Matrix Services (EMS)"</link>
   server, you will need to consent to the terms and conditions. Upon startup, an error
   log entry with a URL to the consent page will be generated.
  </para>
 </section>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="module-services-mjolnir-matrix-synapse-antispam">
  <title>Synapse Antispam Module</title>
  <para>
   A Synapse module is also available to apply the same rulesets the bot
   uses across an entire homeserver.
  </para>
  <para>
   To use the Antispam Module, add <package>matrix-synapse-plugins.matrix-synapse-mjolnir-antispam</package>
   to the Synapse plugin list and enable the <literal>mjolnir.Module</literal> module.
  </para>
<programlisting>
{
  services.matrix-synapse = {
    plugins = with pkgs; [
      matrix-synapse-plugins.matrix-synapse-mjolnir-antispam
    ];
    extraConfig = ''
      modules:
        - module: mjolnir.Module
          config:
            # Prevent servers/users in the ban lists from inviting users on this
            # server to rooms. Default true.
            block_invites: true
            # Flag messages sent by servers/users in the ban lists as spam. Currently
            # this means that spammy messages will appear as empty to users. Default
            # false.
            block_messages: false
            # Remove users from the user directory search by filtering matrix IDs and
            # display names by the entries in the user ban list. Default false.
            block_usernames: false
            # The room IDs of the ban lists to honour. Unlike other parts of Mjolnir,
            # this list cannot be room aliases or permalinks. This server is expected
            # to already be joined to the room - Mjolnir will not automatically join
            # these rooms.
            ban_lists:
              - "!roomid:example.org"
    '';
  };
}
</programlisting>
 </section>
</chapter>
