<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="ch-running">

<title>Running NixOS</title>

<para>This chapter describes various aspects of managing a running
NixOS system, such as how to use the <command>systemd</command>
service manager.</para>


<!--===============================================================-->

<section><title>Service management</title>

<para>In NixOS, all system services are started and monitored using
the systemd program.  Systemd is the “init” process of the system
(i.e. PID 1), the parent of all other processes.  It manages a set of
so-called “units”, which can be things like system services
(programs), but also mount points, swap files, devices, targets
(groups of units) and more.  Units can have complex dependencies; for
instance, one unit can require that another unit must be succesfully
started before the first unit can be started.  When the system boots,
it starts a unit named <literal>default.target</literal>; the
dependencies of this unit cause all system services to be started,
filesystems to be mounted, swap files to be activated, and so
on.</para>

<para>The command <command>systemctl</command> is the main way to
interact with <command>systemd</command>.  Without any arguments, it
shows the status of active units:

<screen>
$ systemctl
-.mount          loaded active mounted   /
swapfile.swap    loaded active active    /swapfile
sshd.service     loaded active running   SSH Daemon
graphical.target loaded active active    Graphical Interface
<replaceable>...</replaceable>
</screen>

</para>

<para>You can ask for detailed status information about a unit, for
instance, the PostgreSQL database service:

<screen>
$ systemctl status postgresql.service
postgresql.service - PostgreSQL Server
          Loaded: loaded (/nix/store/pn3q73mvh75gsrl8w7fdlfk3fq5qm5mw-unit/postgresql.service)
          Active: active (running) since Mon, 2013-01-07 15:55:57 CET; 9h ago
        Main PID: 2390 (postgres)
          CGroup: name=systemd:/system/postgresql.service
                  ├─2390 postgres
                  ├─2418 postgres: writer process
                  ├─2419 postgres: wal writer process
                  ├─2420 postgres: autovacuum launcher process
                  ├─2421 postgres: stats collector process
                  └─2498 postgres: zabbix zabbix [local] idle

Jan 07 15:55:55 hagbard postgres[2394]: [1-1] LOG:  database system was shut down at 2013-01-07 15:55:05 CET
Jan 07 15:55:57 hagbard postgres[2390]: [1-1] LOG:  database system is ready to accept connections
Jan 07 15:55:57 hagbard postgres[2420]: [1-1] LOG:  autovacuum launcher started
Jan 07 15:55:57 hagbard systemd[1]: Started PostgreSQL Server.
</screen>

Note that this shows the status of the unit (active and running), all
the processes belonging to the service, as well as the most recent log
messages from the service.

</para>

<para>Units can be stopped, started or restarted:

<screen>
$ systemctl stop postgresql.service
$ systemctl start postgresql.service
$ systemctl restart postgresql.service
</screen>

These operations are synchronous: they wait until the service has
finished starting or stopping (or has failed).  Starting a unit will
cause the dependencies of that unit to be started as well (if
necessary).</para>

<!-- - cgroups: each service and user session is a cgroup

- cgroup resource management -->

</section>


<!--===============================================================-->

<section><title>Rebooting and shutting down</title>

<para>The system can be shut down (and automatically powered off) by
doing:

<screen>
$ shutdown
</screen>

This is equivalent to running <command>systemctl poweroff</command>.
Likewise, <command>reboot</command> (a.k.a. <command>systemctl
reboot</command>) will reboot the system.</para>

<para>The machine can be suspended to RAM (if supported) using
<command>systemctl suspend</command>, and suspended to disk using
<command>systemctl hibernate</command>.</para>

<para>These commands can be run by any user who is logged in locally,
i.e. on a virtual console or in X11; otherwise, the user is asked for
authentication.</para>

</section>


<!--===============================================================-->

<section><title>User sessions</title>

<para>Systemd keeps track of all users who are logged into the system
(e.g. on a virtual console or remotely via SSH).  The command
<command>loginctl</command> allows quering and manipulating user
sessions.  For instance, to list all user sessions:

<screen>
$ loginctl
   SESSION        UID USER             SEAT
        c1        500 eelco            seat0
        c3          0 root             seat0
        c4        500 alice
</screen>

This shows that two users are logged in locally, while another is
logged in remotely.  (“Seats” are essentially the combinations of
displays and input devices attached to the system; usually, there is
only one seat.)  To get information about a session:

<screen>
$ loginctl session-status c3
c3 - root (0)
           Since: Tue, 2013-01-08 01:17:56 CET; 4min 42s ago
          Leader: 2536 (login)
            Seat: seat0; vc3
             TTY: /dev/tty3
         Service: login; type tty; class user
           State: online
          CGroup: name=systemd:/user/root/c3
                  ├─ 2536 /nix/store/10mn4xip9n7y9bxqwnsx7xwx2v2g34xn-shadow-4.1.5.1/bin/login --
                  ├─10339 -bash
                  └─10355 w3m nixos.org
</screen>

This shows that the user is logged in on virtual console 3.  It also
lists the processes belonging to this session.  Since systemd keeps
track of this, you can terminate a session in a way that ensures that
all the session’s processes are gone:

<screen>
$ loginctl terminate-session c3
</screen>

</para>

</section>


<!--===============================================================-->

<section><title>Control groups</title>

<para>To keep track of the processes in a running system, systemd uses
<emphasis>control groups</emphasis> (cgroups).  A control group is a
set of processes used to allocate resources such as CPU, memory or I/O
bandwidth.  There can be multiple control group hierarchies, allowing
each kind of resource to be managed independently.</para>

<para>The command <command>systemd-cgls</command> lists all control
groups in the <literal>systemd</literal> hierarchy, which is what
systemd uses to keep track of the processes belonging to each service
or user session:

<screen>
$ systemd-cgls
├─user
│ └─eelco
│   └─c1
│     ├─ 2567 -:0
│     ├─ 2682 kdeinit4: kdeinit4 Running...
│     ├─ <replaceable>...</replaceable>
│     └─10851 sh -c less -R
└─system
  ├─httpd.service
  │ ├─2444 httpd -f /nix/store/3pyacby5cpr55a03qwbnndizpciwq161-httpd.conf -DNO_DETACH
  │ └─<replaceable>...</replaceable>
  ├─dhcpcd.service
  │ └─2376 dhcpcd --config /nix/store/f8dif8dsi2yaa70n03xir8r653776ka6-dhcpcd.conf
  └─ <replaceable>...</replaceable>
</screen>

Similarly, <command>systemd-cgls cpu</command> shows the cgroups in
the CPU hierarchy, which allows per-cgroup CPU scheduling priorities.
By default, every systemd service gets its own CPU cgroup, while all
user sessions are in the top-level CPU cgroup.  This ensures, for
instance, that a thousand run-away processes in the
<literal>httpd.service</literal> cgroup cannot starve the CPU for one
process in the <literal>postgresql.service</literal> cgroup.  (By
contrast, it they were in the same cgroup, then the PostgreSQL process
would get 1/1001 of the cgroup’s CPU time.)  You can limit a service’s
CPU share in <filename>configuration.nix</filename>:

<programlisting>
boot.systemd.services.httpd.serviceConfig.CPUShares = 512;
</programlisting>

By default, every cgroup has 1024 CPU shares, so this will halve the
CPU allocation of the <literal>httpd.service</literal> cgroup.</para>

<para>There also is a <literal>memory</literal> hierarchy that
controls memory allocation limits; by default, all processes are in
the top-level cgroup, so any service or session can exhaust all
available memory.  Per-cgroup memory limits can be specified in
<filename>configuration.nix</filename>; for instance, to limit
<literal>httpd.service</literal> to 512 MiB of RAM (excluding swap)
and 640 MiB of RAM (including swap):

<programlisting>
boot.systemd.services.httpd.serviceConfig.MemoryLimit = "512M";
boot.systemd.services.httpd.serviceConfig.ControlGroupAttribute = [ "memory.memsw.limit_in_bytes 640M" ];
</programlisting>

</para>

<para>The command <command>systemd-cgtop</command> shows a
continuously updated list of all cgroups with their CPU and memory
usage.</para>

</section>


<!--===============================================================-->

<section><title>Logging</title>

<para>System-wide logging is provided by systemd’s
<emphasis>journal</emphasis>, which subsumes traditional logging
daemons such as syslogd and klogd.  Log entries are kept in binary
files in <filename>/var/log/journal/</filename>.  The command
<literal>journalctl</literal> allows you to see the contents of the
journal.  For example,

<screen>
$ journalctl -b
</screen>

shows all journal entries since the last reboot.  (The output of
<command>journalctl</command> is piped into <command>less</command> by
default.)  You can use various options and match operators to restrict
output to messages of interest.  For instance, to get all messages
from PostgreSQL:

<screen>
$ journalctl _SYSTEMD_UNIT=postgresql.service
-- Logs begin at Mon, 2013-01-07 13:28:01 CET, end at Tue, 2013-01-08 01:09:57 CET. --
...
Jan 07 15:44:14 hagbard postgres[2681]: [2-1] LOG:  database system is shut down
-- Reboot --
Jan 07 15:45:10 hagbard postgres[2532]: [1-1] LOG:  database system was shut down at 2013-01-07 15:44:14 CET
Jan 07 15:45:13 hagbard postgres[2500]: [1-1] LOG:  database system is ready to accept connections
</screen>

Or to get all messages since the last reboot that have at least a
“critical” severity level:

<screen>
$ journalctl -b -p crit
Dec 17 21:08:06 mandark sudo[3673]: pam_unix(sudo:auth): auth could not identify password for [alice]
Dec 29 01:30:22 mandark kernel[6131]: [1053513.909444] CPU6: Core temperature above threshold, cpu clock throttled (total events = 1)
</screen>

</para>

</section>


</chapter>
